In this video, I want to
在这一讲中
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
tell you about a couple of special
我将介绍一些特殊的矩阵运算
matrix operations, called the
也就是矩阵的逆运算
matrix inverse and the matrix transpose operation.
以及矩阵的转置运算
Let's start by talking about matrix
首先我们从逆矩阵开始
inverse, and as
同往常一样
usual we'll start by thinking about
我们依然先思考一下
how it relates to real numbers.
矩阵运算和实数运算的关系
In the last video, I said
在上一段视频中
that the number one plays the
我讲过 在实数空间中
role of the identity in
数字1扮演了单位矩阵的角色
the space of real numbers because
因为1和任何数相乘
one times anything is equal to itself.
其结果都是那个数本身
It turns out that real numbers
我们都知道
have this property that very
实数有这样的一个性质
number have an, that
那就是每一个实数
each number has an inverse,
都有一个倒数
for example, given the number
举个例子
three, there exists some
对于数字3
number, which happens to
一定存在某个数
be three inverse so that
是3的倒数
that number times gives you
这个倒数乘以3
back the identity element one.
其乘积将得到单位元1
And so to me, inverse of course this is just one third.
当然 这里的逆也就是三分之一
And given some other number,
而对于另一个数
maybe twelve there is
比如说12
some number which is the
那么一定有某个数
inverse of twelve written as
是12的倒数
twelve to the minus one, or
也可以写作12的-1次方
really this is just one twelve.
其实也就是1/12
So that when you multiply these two things together.
因此当你将这两个数相乘的时候
the product is equal to
其结果依然是等于1
the identity element one again.
或者可以称为单位元1
Now it turns out that in
然而事实上 在实数空间内
the space of real numbers, not everything has an inverse.
并非所有实数都有倒数
For example the number zero
比如说数字0就没有倒数
does not have an inverse, right?
是吧？
Because zero's a zero inverse, one over zero that's undefined.
因为0的倒数 也就是1/0 是没有意义的
Like this one over zero is not well defined.
像这里 1除以0是未被定义的
And what we want to
在这一节剩下的内容中
do, in the rest of this
我们将要解决的一个问题
slide, is figure out what does
是求解一个矩阵的逆
it mean to compute the inverse of a matrix.
是什么意思
Here's the idea: If
概念如下
A is a n by
如果A是一个矩阵
n matrix, and it
其维度为m行m列
has an inverse, I will say
那么A矩阵有其逆矩阵
a bit more about that later, then
后面我还会详细介绍这一点
the inverse is going to
那么这个逆矩阵
be written A to the
可以写成
minus one and A
矩阵A的-1次方
times this inverse, A to
同时 矩阵A乘以它的逆矩阵
the minus one, is going to
A的-1次方
equal to A inverse times
也等于A的-1次方乘以A
A, is going to
其结果将等于
give us back the identity matrix.
单位矩阵
Okay?
对吧？
Only matrices that are
只有维度是m行m列的矩阵
m by m for some the idea of M having inverse.
才有其逆矩阵
So, a matrix is
因此
M by M, this is also
如果一个矩阵的维度是m行m列
called a square matrix and
那么这个矩阵也可以称之为方阵
it's called square because
称其为方阵是因为
the number of rows is equal to the number of columns.
这类矩阵的行数和列数相等
Right and it turns out
好的
only square matrices have inverses,
实际上只有方阵才有逆矩阵
so A is a square
所以 如果A是一个方阵
matrix, is m by m,
其维度是m行m列
on inverse this equation over here.
那么它将满足这个等式
Let's look at a concrete example,
接下来我们看一个具体的例子
so let's say I
假设说
have a matrix, three, four,
我们有这样一个矩阵 3 4
two, sixteen.
2 16
So this is a two by
这是一个2行2列的矩阵
two matrix, so it's
因此这个矩阵
a square matrix and so this
是一个方阵
may just could have an and
因此这个矩阵可以有它的逆矩阵
it turns out that I
假如说
happen to know the inverse
这个矩阵的逆矩阵是
of this matrix is zero point
0.4
four, minus zero point
-0.1
one, minus zero point
-0.05
zero five, zero zero seven five.
0.075
And if I take this matrix
那么如果我用这个逆矩阵
and multiply these together it
和原来的矩阵相乘
turns out what I get
那么
is the two by
我们将得到的结果
two identity matrix, I,
是一个2行2列的单位矩阵I
this is I two by two.
这就是矩阵I 维度是2行2列
Okay?
没问题吧？
And so on this slide,
在这张幻灯片上
you know this matrix is
这个矩阵就是矩阵A
the matrix A, and this matrix is the matrix A-inverse.
这个矩阵就是A的逆矩阵
And it turns out
结果是
if that you are computing A
如果你要计算A乘以A的逆矩阵
times A-inverse, it turns out
或者说
if you compute A-inverse times
A的逆矩阵乘以A
A you also get back the identity matrix.
你将得到一个单位矩阵
So how did I
那么
find this inverse or how
怎样得到这个逆矩阵呢
did I come up with this inverse over here?
或者说我是怎么知道这个逆矩阵的呢？
It turns out that sometimes
实际上有时候你可以
you can compute inverses by hand
自己用笔算出来
but almost no one does that these days.
但可能现在没多少人这么求逆矩阵了
And it turns out there is
实际上我们有很多很好的软件
very good numerical software for
可以用来进行数学运算
taking a matrix and computing its inverse.
能很容易地对矩阵进行求逆运算
So again, this is one of
因此 同样地
those things where there are lots
对于这个问题
of open source libraries that
你可以在很多主流的编程环境中实现
you can link to from any
这些环境一般都有很多开源库
of the popular programming languages to compute inverses of matrices.
你可以直接运用来求解逆矩阵
Let me show you a quick example.
这里我举一个简单的例子
How I actually computed this inverse,
来说明一下怎样求逆矩阵
and what I did was I used software called Optive.
我将使用一个叫Octave的软件
So let me bring that up.
打开这个软件
We will see a lot about Optive later.
之后我们还会更多地用到Octave
Let me just quickly show you an example.
这里我只是很快地举一个例子
Set my matrix A to
定义一个矩阵A
be equal to that matrix on
对它赋值为左边幻灯片上的矩阵
the left, type three four
键入3 4 2 16
two sixteen, so that's my matrix A right.
这就是我的A矩阵了
This is matrix 34,
这就是矩阵 3 4
216 that I have down
2 16
here on the left.
也就是左边那个矩阵
And, the software lets me compute
使用这个软件
the inverse of A very easily.
我能够很容易得到A的逆矩阵
It's like P over A equals this.
就像这样直接键入pinv(A)
And so, this is right,
这样
this matrix here on my
我们得到了结果
four minus, on my one, and so on.
0.4 -0.1 等等
This given the numerical
这里得到的是
solution to what is the
A的逆矩阵的近似解
inverse of A. So let me
我可以这样写
just write, inverse of A
定义一个变量inverseOFA
equals P inverse of
其值等于 pinv(A)
A over that I
那么inverseOFA的值就是这样
can now just verify that A
现在我们可以证明一下
times A inverse the identity
A乘以A的逆矩阵结果是单位矩阵
is, type A times the
键入 A 乘以
inverse of A and
A的逆矩阵
the result of that is
这样得到的结果
this matrix and this is
是这样的一个矩阵
one one on the diagonal
主对角线是1和1
and essentially ten to
副对角线不是1
the minus seventeen, ten to the
但是基本上10的-17次方
minus sixteen, so Up to
10的-16次方
numerical precision, up to
这里由于计算精度的问题
a little bit of round off
由于计算机在寻找最佳结果时
error that my computer
由于进行了四舍五入圆整
had in finding optimal matrices
所以产生了一点点误差
and these numbers off the
所以这些副对角线上的数字
diagonals are essentially zero
实际上也近似等于0
so A times the inverse is essentially the identity matrix.
因此矩阵A和其逆矩阵相乘的结果就是单位矩阵
Can also verify the inverse of
我们也可以证明
A times A is also
A的逆矩阵乘以A
equal to the identity,
其结果也是单位矩阵
ones on the diagonals and values
主对角线上都是1
that are essentially zero except
副对角线上的数有小数
for a little bit of round
但四舍五入圆整一下
dot error on the off diagonals.
实际上其值也等于0
If a definition that the inverse
关于逆矩阵的定义
of a matrix is, I had
我需要强调一点
this caveat first it must
首先
always be a square matrix, it
矩阵必须是方阵
had this caveat, that if
注意这里
A has an inverse, exactly what
如果A有其逆矩阵
matrices have an inverse
究竟什么矩阵有其逆矩阵的问题
is beyond the scope of this
已经超出了这节线性代数复习课
linear algebra for review that one
所讨论的范畴
intuition you might take away
但有一点
that just as the
你能理解的是
number zero doesn't have an
数字0没有倒数
inverse, it turns out
因此
that if A is say the
如果矩阵A中
matrix of all zeros, then
所有元素都为0
this matrix A also does
那么这个矩阵A
not have an inverse because there's
依然没有逆矩阵
no matrix there's no A
因为没有这样的A矩阵
inverse matrix so that this
能使得这个矩阵
matrix times some other
乘以另一个矩阵
matrix will give you the
其值能得到单位矩阵
identity matrix so this matrix of
所以
all zeros, and there
所有元素都为0的矩阵
are a few other matrices with properties similar to this.
以及一些其他类似这样的矩阵
That also don't have an inverse.
它们都没有逆矩阵
But it turns out that
但是实际上
in this review I don't
在这节复习课中
want to go too deeply into what
我不想太深入地介绍
it means matrix have an
矩阵的逆矩阵有何意义等问题
inverse but it turns
但是实际上
out for our machine learning
对于我们机器学习的应用来讲
application this shouldn't be
这一点不应成为问题
an issue or more precisely
具体来讲
for the learning algorithms where
对于某种机器学习算法
this may be an to namely
可能会碰到这种问题的讨论
whether or not an inverse matrix
是否存在逆矩阵这样的问题
appears and I will tell when
在我们碰到这种学习算法时
we get to those learning algorithms
我再告诉你
just what it means for an
一种算法到底有没有逆矩阵
algorithm to have or not
究竟应该怎样理解
have an inverse and how to fix it in case.
以及应该怎样解决具体的问题
Working with matrices that don't
比如怎样处理
have inverses.
矩阵的逆矩阵不存在的问题
But the intuition if you
不过你至少可以这样理解
want is that you can
在某种意义上
think of matrices as not
你可以把那些
have an inverse that is somehow
没有逆矩阵的矩阵
too close to zero in some sense.
想成是非常近似为0
So, just to wrap
最后再讲一点
up the terminology, matrix that
逆矩阵不存在的矩阵
don't have an inverse Sometimes called
它的专有名词是
a singular matrix or degenerate
奇异矩阵
matrix and so this
或者叫退化矩阵
matrix over here is an
因此这里这个矩阵
example zero zero zero matrix.
这个零矩阵
is an example of a matrix that is singular, or a matrix that is degenerate.
就是一个奇异矩阵 或者说退化矩阵的例子
Finally, the last special
最后 还有一种矩阵运算
matrix operation I want to
我想给大家介绍的
tell you about is to do matrix transpose.
是矩阵的转置运算
So suppose I have
假设我们有矩阵A
matrix A, if I compute
那么A的转置矩阵
the transpose of A, that's what I get here on the right.
可以写成右边这个矩阵
This is a transpose which is
这就是矩阵A的转置矩阵
written and A superscript T,
写法是A加上一个上标的T
and the way you compute
计算转置矩阵的方法
the transpose of a matrix is as follows.
如下所示
To get a transpose I am going
要得到转置矩阵
to first take the first
首先我取出A矩阵的第一行
row of A one to zero.
1 2 0
That becomes this first column of this transpose.
它们将成为转置矩阵的第一列
And then I'm going to take
接下来
the second row of A,
我再取出矩阵A的第二行
3 5 9, and that becomes the second column.
3 5 9
of the matrix A transpose.
它们将成为转置矩阵的第二列
And another way of
你也可以这样想
thinking about how the computer transposes
求解转置矩阵
is as if you're taking this
实际上可以看作
sort of 45 degree axis
画一条45度的斜线
and you are mirroring or you
然后你以这条线求镜像
are flipping the matrix along that 45 degree axis.
或者以这条45度线为轴进行翻转
so here's the more formal
因此我们可以得到
definition of a matrix transpose.
关于矩阵转置的正式定义
Let's say A is a m by n matrix.
假设矩阵A是一个m行n列的矩阵
And let's let B equal A
并且假设矩阵B等于A的转置
transpose and so BA transpose like so.
就像这样
Then B is going to
那么B将是一个
be a n by m matrix
n行m列的矩阵
with the dimensions reversed so
两个矩阵的维度是相反的
here we have a 2x3 matrix.
这里我们的A矩阵是2行3列的
And so the transpose becomes a
那么A的转置矩阵B
3x2 matrix, and moreover,
将是一个3行2列的矩阵
the BIJ is equal to AJI.
此外 Bij等于Aji
So the IJ element of this
也就是说
matrix B is going to be
矩阵B的ij元素
the JI element of that
是等于A矩阵的ji元素
earlier matrix A. So for
我们来举个例子
example, B 1 2
B12这个元素
is going to be equal
将等于
to, look at this
请看这个矩阵
matrix, B 1 2 is going to be equal to
B12元素将等于
this element 3 1st row, 2nd column.
A矩阵中 第一行第二列的元素3
And that equal to this, which
那么这个元素
is a two one, second
也就是等于A21
row first column, right, which
A矩阵中第二行第一列的元素
is equal to two and some
也就是2
of the example B 3
再举个例子
2, right, that's B
B32这个元素
3 2 is this element 9,
也就是9
and that's equal to
是等于
a two three which is
A23这个元素
this element up here, nine.
也就是这个元素 也是等于9的
And so that wraps up
好的
the definition of what it
这样我们就介绍了
means to take the transpose
怎样求一个矩阵的转置矩阵
of a matrix and that
以及它的正式定义
in fact concludes our linear algebra review.
这也是我们的线性代数复习课的最后一节
So by now hopefully you know
现在你应该已经掌握
how to add and subtract
如何进行矩阵的加法运算
matrices as well as
以及乘法运算
multiply them and you
同时
also know how, what are
你也应该了解
the definitions of the inverses
矩阵的逆运算
and transposes of a matrix
和转置运算的定义
and these are the main operations
这些都是这门课中
used in linear algebra
需要用到的线性代数中
for this course.
最基本的一些运算
In case this is the first time you are seeing this material.
也许这是你第一次观看我们的视频
I know this was a lot
我知道这里一下子讲了
of linear algebra material all presented
很多线性代数的知识
very quickly and it's a
讲的很多也讲的很快
lot to absorb but
可能需要一点时间来消化
if you there's no need
你没有必要记住
to memorize all the definitions
我们刚刚讲过的
we just went through and if
所有那些定义
you download the copy of either
如果你从课程网站上
these slides or of the
下载了这些幻灯片
lecture notes from the course website.
或者讲义
and use either the slides or
并且使用它们
the lecture notes as a reference
作为一个参考内容
then you can always refer back
那么你可以随时返回
to the definitions and to figure
查看这些定义和概念
out what are these matrix
随时理解这些矩阵的乘法 转置
multiplications, transposes and so on definitions.
等等这些运算的概念
And the lecture notes on the course website also
同时 课程官网的讲义中
has pointers to additional
我们也提供了链接
resources linear algebra which
也是一些其他的线性代数资料
you can use to learn more about linear algebra by yourself.
你可以自己点击学习
And next with these new tools.
接下来 运用这些所学的工具
We'll be able in the next
在接下来的几段视频中
few videos to develop more powerful
我们将介绍
forms of linear regression that
非常重要的线性回归
can view of a lot
我们会看到更多的数据
more data, a lot more
更多的特征
features, a lot more training
以及更多的训练样本
examples and later on
再往后
after the new regression we'll actually
在介绍线性回归之后
continue using these linear
我们还将继续使用这些线代工具
algebra tools to derive more
来推导一些
powerful learning algorithims as well
更加强大的学习算法